{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "John Shipton chaired a political party founded by this man to contest the 2013 Australian Senate elections. An organization founded by this man gained prominence after publishing the “Collateral Murder” video, along with other materials provided by Chelsea Manning. In 2010, Sweden requested that this man be extradited on allegations of sexual assault. This man was granted asylum by Ecuador in 2012, and currently resides in its London embassy. For ten points, name this whistleblower who founded WikiLeaks.",
      "answer": "Julian Paul Assange"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, Minnijean Brown had a purse filled with locks thrown at her and Melba Pattillo was subject to an acid attack, despite the presence of the 101st Airborne Division. Virgil Blossom was removed as Superintendent shortly before this city underwent “The Lost Year,” caused by Orval Faubus’s pledge to close its public high schools and reopen them as private schools. In 1957, nine African American students successfully integrated Central High School in, for ten points, what Arkansas city?",
      "answer": "Little Rock"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the age of four, this figure visited Pope Leo IV, who supposedly “anointed” this man as king. From a later pope, Marinus, this man may have received a fragment of the true cross, according to this man’s bishop Asser. He and a rival split the kingdom of Mercia, the eastern half of which joined the kingdom of East Anglia, and this king later rid Wessex of the Danes. For ten points, name this only English monarch to be stylized “the Great.”",
      "answer": "Alfred the Great or Alfred I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Physicists often use the “Left step” alternative to this system; another famous alternative was created by Theodor Benfey in a spiral shape. The most recent change to this system included an addition named for the state of Tennessee. This system initially had blank spaces left for “eka-germanium” and other undiscovered entries. Dmitri Mendeleev introduced, for ten points, what system that organizes the 118 chemical elements?",
      "answer": "periodic table of the elements"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man led a campaign to boycott school textbooks produced by Harper’s to blackmail the company into firing one of its employees. The Committee of Seventy investigated the actions of this man. During this man’s trial, he fled home arrest and escaped to Spain, but he was recognized from his depiction in a political cartoon drawn by Thomas Nast. For ten points, identify this corrupt leader of Tammany Hall.",
      "answer": "William M. “Boss” Tweed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The loser of this event began it wearing a “Sugar Daddy” jacket, having been sponsored by the candy. This event, which took place four months after a similar event lost by Margaret Court, was watched by 50 million people and ended in straight sets. A 2017 film starring Emma Stone and Steve Carell depicts, for ten points, what 1973 match in which Billie Jean King defeated Bobby Riggs, helping spark interest in women’s tennis?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Sexes",
        "descriptive answers related to Billie Jean King playing/defeating/etc. Bobby Riggs before “Billie” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this kingdom founded the League of Corinth after crushing the Sacred Band of Thebes at Chaeronea [care-oh-nay-uh]. After a leader of this empire died, its generals feuded in the Wars of the Diadochi [die-ah-doe-kee], which produced the Ptolemaic Kingdom and Seleucid Empire. A leader of this kingdom defeated Darius III at the Battle of Issus before conquering Babylon at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten points, name this kingdom led by Philip II and Alexander the Great.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Macedonia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician from this state sought to assimilate Native Americans in his Dawes Act. Another politician from this state gave the Seventh of March speech supporting the Compromise of 1850 and declared “Liberty and union, now and forever” in a reply to Hayne. After a senator from this state denounced the Kansas-Nebraska Act, South Carolina’s Preston Brooks beat him with a cane. For ten points, name this state represented by Charles Sumner and Daniel Webster.",
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event’s lesser known victims include the Batwa pygmy people. The French attempted to alleviate this event through a safe zone in Operation Turquoise. The destruction of an aircraft carrying Juvenal Habyarimana was used as a pretext to begin this event, which ended when Paul Kagame’s [kah-gah-may’s] Patriotic Front defeated the Interahamwe and recaptured Kigali. For ten points, name this 1994 atrocity in which the Hutus targeted Tutsis in an East African country.",
      "answer": [
        "Rwandan Genocide",
        "descriptions of the genocide of the Tutsis/by the Hutus until “Hutu” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Highwayman William Brazelton operated around this city in the mid-19th century. Hugh O’Connor founded this non-Mexican city as a military fort in 1775. McKale Center in this city is home to its state’s flagship university. Saguaro National Park is located just west of this city, where Jared Lee Loughner attempted to assassinate Representative Gabrielle Giffords in 2011. For ten points, name this home of the University of Arizona, the second largest city in Arizona.",
      "answer": "Tucson, Arizona"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler failed to negotiate a trade agreement with Japan after storms blew a Japanese sea captain into this ruler’s territory. This ruler established the first publicly funded higher-education institution for women, the Smolny Institute. She eliminated required military service for the nobility and placed Stanislas Poniatowski, her former lover, on the throne of Poland in 1763. This ruler assumed power after a coup d’etat against her husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this “Great” Empress of Russia.",
        "answer": "Catherine the Great or Catherine II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine’s scholarly patronage included support for this French playwright and philosopher, the chief editor of the Encyclop´edie.",
        "answer": "Denis Diderot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bricks of this color were used in the background of the mosaics on the Ishtar Gate to imitate a mineral mined near Sar-i Sang. Tin-glazed pottery of this color over white was produced by artists in 17th century Delft. This color names a period in which works like The Old Guitarist were created by a somber Pablo Picasso. For ten points, name this color that, during the Middle Ages, was produced in artworks by crushing lapis lazuli into pigments like ultramarine.",
        "answer": [
          "blue",
          "specific types of blue, such as ultramarine and lapis lazuli before mentioned BONUS:LapislazulifromtheSar-iSangmineswastradedalongtheWakhanCorridor,whichiscontrolled by this country and gives it a short border with China. ANSWER: Islamic Republic of Afghanistan 3 This event took place in its chosen city because the Justizpalast was one of the few undamaged buildings available. Alfred Jodl , Hans Frank, and Wilhelm Frick were among those convicted during this event, as was Hermann Goering, who was found hanged in his prison cell the day before his scheduled execution. For ten points, name this series of post-World War II military tribunals that convicted former Nazis of war crimes. ANSWER: Nuremberg Trials",
          "word forms and elaborations"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Deputy Fuhrer was also put on trial at Nuremberg, having fled Germany in 1941 to negotiate peace talks in Scotland. After the trials, he was imprisoned in Spandau Prison until his 1987 suicide.",
        "answer": "Rudolf Hess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s The Practice and Theory of Bolshevism reflected his disappointment with the Soviet Union after a 1920 visit, which included a meeting with Lenin. This proponent of logical atomism supervised Ludwig Wittgenstein’s Ph.D. thesis. This philosopher’s namesake “teapot” is often used to shift the burden of proof in religious debates. With Alfred North Whitehead, this philosopher attempted to synthesize the foundations of mathematics in 1910. For ten points, name this British philosopher, the co-author of Principia Mathematica.",
        "answer": "Bertrand Russell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bertrand Russell co-wrote a political manifesto with Albert Einstein concerning this subject in 1955. Treaties concerning this subject included SALT I, SALT II, and START.",
        "answer": [
          "nuclear weapons",
          "answers about nuclear proliferation, nuclear weapon testing, nuclear warfare, etc.",
          "specific types of nuclear weapons"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Philip Murray represented workers in this industry, who went on strike in April 1952 in response to Harry Truman’s nationalization of its production facilities, a decision that was quickly ruled unconstitutional in the Youngstown case. ArcelorMittal, the world’s largest producer of this commodity, absorbed a major American company in this industry, Bethlehem, during the 2000s. For ten points, name this industrial commodity that created much of Andrew Carnegie’s wealth in Pittsburgh.",
        "answer": "steel industry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Andrew Carnegie’s steel fortune was fueled by this 19th century technological development, an industrial process that allowed production of steel from pig iron.",
        "answer": "Bessemer process"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a novel in this genre, the prostitute Lorena suffers from PTSD after she is kidnapped and sexually assaulted by Blue Duck. A novel in this genre follows Jane Withersteen, who escapes from a Mormon commune. Books in this genre include Larry McMurtry’s Lonesome Dove and Zane Grey’s Riders of the Purple Sage. For ten points, what is the genre of many Louis L’Amour novels featuring cowboys?",
        "answer": [
          "Westerns",
          "Western fiction",
          "Frontier fiction"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This contemporary author of Western fiction wrote about the real-life Glanton scalp hunting gang in Blood Meridian and the fictional Anton Chigurh in No Country for Old Men.",
        "answer": "Cormac McCarthy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Forces from what is now this country defeated the Mongols at the Battle of Ain Jalut under the command of Baibars, a Mamluk slave soldier. During the Crisis of the Third Century, Zenobia conquered this “breadbasket” region and claimed descent from its most recent independent ruler, a member of the Greek Ptolemaic dynasty who legendarily committed suicide via snakebite. For ten points, name this region once ruled by Cleopatra along the Nile River.",
        "answer": "Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Mamluks seized control of Egypt from the Ayyubid dynasty, which was founded by this general who fought in the Third Crusade.",
        "answer": "Saladin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1950, this politician distributed a “Pink Sheet” attacking the voting record of his opponent, Helen Gahagan Douglas. After this man lost a 1962 election to Pat Brown, this man claimed to give his last press conference and told the media they “won’t have [him] to kick around anymore.” This man refused to wear makeup in the first televised presidential debate, which pitted him against John F. Kennedy. Dwight Eisenhower’s Vice President was, for ten points, what politician who resigned as President after the Watergate scandal?",
        "answer": "Richard Milhous Nixon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nixon’s 1962 loss to Pat Brown was an election for this office, which had earlier been held by Earl Warren.",
        "answer": "Governor of California"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Education",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "German-inspired grade before first grade, introduced in the US by Elizabeth Peabody.",
          "answer": "kindergarten"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massachusetts capital city whose Latin School was the first public school in the US.",
          "answer": "Boston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of people who were sent to college via the GI Bill after World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "veterans",
            "anything related to serving in the US armed forces, such as soldiers, etc.",
            "GI if given before read"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Specific scientific subject that was illegally taught in Tennessee, leading to the Scopes “Monkey Trial.”",
          "answer": "human evolution or human natural selection"
        },
        {
          "question": "Settlement house founded by Ellen Gates Starr and Jane Addams that provided vocational education to women in Chicago.",
          "answer": "Hull House"
        },
        {
          "question": "2001 act that set a national agenda of results-based education and controversially sought 100% proficiency.",
          "answer": "No Child Left Behind Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massachusettspoliticianwhoarguededucationshouldbeuniversal,public,andnon-religious,inspiring the 19th century Common School movement.",
          "answer": "Horace Mann"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pragmatic reformer who argued in Democracy and Education that education bridges the gap between the immature and experienced.",
          "answer": "John Dewey"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Roman Gladiators",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Amphitheater in Rome where the largest gladiatorial games were held.",
          "answer": "Colosseum or the Flavian Amphitheater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horse-drawn vehicles that served as a platform for some gladiators.",
          "answer": "chariots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Social class for many gladiators, especially foreign ones captured as spoils of war.",
          "answer": "slaves or servus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Symbol given by spectators to determine whether the winner of a fight should kill or spare the loser.",
          "answer": [
            "a turned thumb or pollice verso",
            "anything related to turning your thumb a certain way"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of gladiatorial combat done in a naumachia [now-mock-ee-uh].",
          "answer": [
            "naval battle",
            "anything to do with ships, boats, the sea, filling the Colosseum with water, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Special weapon used by the lightly-armored retiarius against secutores. Either of two English answers is acceptable.",
          "answer": "net and/or trident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gladiator-related business operated by lanistas.",
          "answer": [
            "training schools",
            "ludus",
            "ludi"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mesopotamia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern capital of Iraq where artifacts were damaged in the Gulf Wars.",
          "answer": "Baghdad"
        },
        {
          "question": "World wonder built in Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar for his homesick wife.",
          "answer": "Hanging Gardens of Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Fertile” shape of the Mesopotamian region where early civilization grew.",
          "answer": "Fertile Crescent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Important river that meets the Euphrates [yoo-fray-teez] at the Shatt al-Arab in southern Iraq.",
          "answer": "Tigris River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writing style developed in Mesopotamia, using a stylus to make wedge shapes on tablets.",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century BC Neo-Assyrian ruler who collected 30,000 of those tablets in a library now held in Britain.",
          "answer": "Ashurbanipal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First urban civilization in Mesopotamia, led during the Uruk Dynasty by Gilgamesh.",
          "answer": "Sumerians"
        },
        {
          "question": "First ruler of Akkad, a “Great” ruler who once served as cupbearer.",
          "answer": "Sargon the Great or Sargon I"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the construction of the Overland Telegraph Line, this site was first explored by Ernest Giles and William Gosse. This site was secured by Bob Hawke in a 99-year lease that controversially allowed it to be (20 pts)",
        "climbed by visitors. This site forms a national park along with the Kata Tjuta, a series of formations also called the Olgas. This site was originally named in honor of Henry (10 pts)",
        "Ayers. For ten points, name this sandstone formation that is sacred to the Anangu Aboriginal people of Australia’s Northern Territory."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Uluru",
        "Ayers Rock before “Ayers” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An emperor of this dynasty was captured by the Oirat Esen Tayisi in the Tumu Crisis. Li Zicheng of the Shun Dynasty helped cause the downfall of this empire, which was founded by the (20 pts)",
        "Hongwu Emperor. This dynasty, which was founded after the Red Turban revolt, was led by the Yongle Emperor, who built the (10 pts)",
        "Forbidden City and sponsored several treasure voyages under the eunuch Zheng He. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that followed the Qing and was known its for blue and white ceramic vases."
      ],
      "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man selected John Kern as his running mate in one election, in which his slogan was “Shall the People Rule?” This man, a regular on the Chatauqua circuit, resigned as (20 pts)",
        "Secretary of State in protest of Woodrow Wilson’s pro-war stance. He rose to prominence after delivering an oration at an 1896 convention supporting (10 pts)",
        "bimetallism, demanding that Republicans not “crucify mankind” on the title object. For ten points, name this Democratic presidential candidate who delivered the “Cross of Gold” speech."
      ],
      "answer": "William Jennings Bryan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Mexican Expedition, six members of this group bayonet charged 3,000 Mexican soldiers at the Battle of Camaron. The “spilled blood” provision automatically grants members of this group (20 pts)",
        "citizenship after they are wounded in combat. This organization was formed after the July Revolution overthrew the House of Bourbon. During World War II, this section of the military refused to cooperate with the (10 pts)",
        "Vichy government. For ten points, name this branch of the French military primarily consisting of non-French volunteers."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "French Foreign Legion",
        "FFL",
        "L´egion E´trang`ere",
        "LE"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Contrary to popular legend about this composer, audiences actually requested “Immenso Jehova” as an encore, though mourners at this man’s funeral did break out into “Va, pensiero.” That song, the chorus of the (20 pts)",
        "Hebrew slaves from this composer’s Nabucco, became an anthem of the (10 pts)",
        "Risorgimento, during which this man’s name was used as an acronym in support of King Victor Emmanuel. For ten points, name this 19th-century Italian composer also known for the operas La Traviata and Aida."
      ],
      "answer": "Giuseppe Verdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, the brother of Aeschylus [ess-kuh-luss] was cut down while attempting to pull a ship to shore by hand. Datis and Artaphernes were aided in this battle by a vengeful (20 pts)",
        "Hippias, who had been exiled earlier by the winning side. Callimachus cast the deciding vote in favor of launching this battle, which resulted in a rout of (10 pts)",
        "Darius’ men. Athens was victorious over Persia in, for ten points, what 490 BC battle that inspires the name of a lengthy footrace?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a speech at the Sorbonne in 1948, this activist outlined her work on a document that describes the “equal and inalienable rights of all members of the human family,” the (20 pts)",
        "Universal Declaration of Human Rights. When Marian Anderson was denied a concert at Constitutional Hall by the Daughters of the American Revolution, this woman resigned from the D.A.R. and organized a concert for Anderson at the (10 pts)",
        "Lincoln Memorial. For ten points, name this human rights activist who served as First Lady for 12 years alongside her husband, Franklin Delano."
      ],
      "answer": "Eleanor Roosevelt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A probably forged religious text from this country follows its native god of the underworld, Veles. The restoration of the withershins ritual movement in this country in the 17th-century led to the breaking off of the “Old (20 pts)",
        "Believers” here. This nation’s church, which is currently led by Kirill, was reformed in the 17th century by (10 pts)",
        "Patriarch Nikon. This country’s capital contains a church known for its colorful “onion” domes. For ten points, name this home of St. Basil’s Cathedral in Moscow."
      ],
      "answer": "Russia"
    }
  ]
}